A Guide to the Supreme Court of Virginia Oaths of Office, 1935-1985; 2007
Virginia State Law Library, Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
Supreme Court of Virginia Archives
Supreme Court of Virginia Oaths of Office, 1935-1985; 2007
Supreme Court of Virginia Archives, Virginia State Law Library
00028932
0.45 cu. ft. (1 box)
Virginia. Supreme Court. Office of the Clerk.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
These records were transferred from the Clerk's office to the State Law Library in 2006.
Historical Information
The Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia was created by an act of the new General Assembly in 1779. Although the Supreme Court of Virginia possesses both original and appellate jurisdiction, its primary function is to review decisions of lower courts, including the Court of Appeals, from which appeals have been allowed.
Section 49-1 of the Code of Virginia requires justices to take an oath as on officer of the Commonwealth. Pursuant to Section 49-3 of the Code of Virginia, justices may be sworn in by a judge, clerk, or deputy clerk of a court of record; a judge of a district court; the Secretary of the Commonwealth, or a State Corporation Commissioner. Justices are elected by the legislature to 12-year terms. Chief justices are elected by a majority vote of the other Supreme court justices and serve a four-year term.
The Supreme Court of Virginia Clerk's Office receives, processes, and maintains permanent records of all appeals and other official documents filed with the Court. The Clerk also maintains records of qualified attorneys and other administrative records.
Scope and Content
The collection (not comprehensive) contains oaths of office of Supreme Court justices between 1935 and 2012. The collection also contains the oaths taken by Supreme Court Clerk Maury B. Watts, 1937; Deputy Clerk Bryan L. Clarke, 1957; Clerk Allen L. Lucy, 1977; Attorney General Kenneth C. Patty, 1957; and J. Lindsay Almond, Roanoke (city) Hustings Court judge, 1941.
Arrangement
Alphabetical.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth.; Virginia. Supreme Court.; Virginia. Supreme Court. Office of the Clerk.
Subjects:
Judges--Virginia.; Virginia -- Supreme Court -- History -- 20th century.; Clerks of court -- Virginia -- 20th century.
Genre/Form:
Oaths -- Virginia.
Contents List
- J. Lindsay Almond, Roanoke (city) Hustings court judge, 1946, 1947, 1963 (Folder 1)
- Justice Archibald Chapman Buchanan, 1946, 1947, 1963 (Folder 2)
- Chief Justice Harry Lee Carrico, 1962, 1966, 1979, 1981 (Folder 3)
- Bryan L. Clark, Deputy Clerk, 1958 (Folder 4)
- Justice George Moffett Cochran, 1969, 1970, 1973, 1974, 1975 (Folder 5)
- Chief Justice John William Eggleston, 1935, 1961, 1970 (Folder 6)
- Justice Thomas Christian Gordon, Jr., 1965 (Folder 7)
- Justice Herbert Bailey Gregory, 1942 (Folder 8)
- Justice Alexander Marrs Harman, 1969, 1970, 1975 (Folder 9)
- Justice Albertis S. Harrison, Jr., 1970, 1971 (Folder 10)
- Chief Justice Leroy Rountree Hassell, 2007 (Folder 11)
- Chief Justice Henry Winston Holt, 1942 (Folder 12)
- Chief Justice Edward Wren Hudgins, 1942, 1954 (Folder 13)
- Chief Justice Lawrence Warren I'Anson, 1958, 1978 (Folder 14)
- Allen L. Lucy, Clerk, 1977 (Folder 15)
- Justice Willis Dance Miller, 1947, 1948, 1955 (Folder 16)
- Kenneth C. Patty, Attorney General, 1957 (Folder 17)
- Justice Richard Harding Poff, 1972, 1985 (Folder 18)
- Justice Lemuel Franklin Smith, 1951, 1953 (Folder 19)
- Justice Harold Fleming Snead, 1957, 1958, 1964 (Folder 20)
- Chief Justice Claude Vernon Spratley, 1947, 1959 (Folder 21)
- Justice Abram Penn Staples, 1947, 1948 (Folder 22)
- Justice John Charles Thomas, 1983 (Folder 23)
- Justice William Carrington Thompson, 1980 (Folder 24)
- Maury B. Watts, Clerk, 1937 (Folder 25)
- Justice Henry Hudson Whiting, 1987 (Folder 26)
- Justice Kennon Cathness Whittle, 1951, 1952, 1954 (Folder 27)